<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2006 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN11A-1150</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0555  Neural networks, fuzzy logic, machine learning</Keyword>
    <Keyword>3094  Instruments and techniques</Keyword>
    <Keyword>3235  Persistence, memory, correlations, clustering</Keyword>
    <Keyword>5194  Instruments and techniques</Keyword>
    <Keyword>8036  Paleoseismology</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>The standard methodology to describe, classify and correlate geologic materials in the field or lab rely on physical inspection of samples, sometimes with the assistance of conventional analytical techniques (e. g. XRD, microscopy, particle size analysis). This is commonly both time-consuming and inherently subjective. Many geological materials share identical visible properties (e.g. fine grained materials, alteration minerals) and therefore cannot be mapped using the human eye alone. Recent investigations have shown that ground- based hyperspectral imaging provides an effective method to study and digitally store stratigraphic and structural data from cores or field exposures. Neural networks and Naive Bayesian classifiers supply a variety of well-established techniques towards pattern recognition, especially for data examples with high- dimensionality input-outputs. In this poster, we present a new methodology for automatic mapping of sedimentary stratigraphy in the lab (drill cores, samples) or the field (outcrops, exposures) using short wave infrared (SWIR) hyperspectral images and these two supervised classification algorithms. High-spatial/spectral resolution data from large sediment samples (drill cores) from a paleoseismic excavation site were collected using a portable hyperspectral scanner with 245 continuous channels measured across the 960 to 2404 nm spectral range. The data were corrected for geometric and radiometric distortions and pre-processed to obtain reflectance at each pixel of the images. We built an example set using hundreds of reflectance spectra collected from the sediment core images. The examples were grouped into eight classes corresponding to materials found in the samples. We constructed two additional example sets by computing the 2-norm normalization, the derivative of the smoothed original reflectance examples. Each example set was divided into four subsets: training, training test, verification and validation. A multi-layer perceptron with variable architecture and a Na&amp;iuml;ve Bayesian classifier were trained to construct the classification models. Then, we computed the classification accuracy of our models using the validation sets. For the original reflectance set, our best model achieved a 98.4 % classification accuracy. The 2-norm normalized reflectance training set produced 97 % classification accuracy and the derivatives training sets generated models with 97 % (every point derivative) and 97.6 % (every five points derivative) classification accuracy. The outputs of the best model were used to classify the core images. We generated classification images of all the samples and compared them against the real samples for an ultimate qualitative verification of the classification. The results of this work show that reflectance spectra combined with neural networks or Naive Bayesian classifieres can be used to properly discern and classify sediments of very similar composition and grain size. Quantitative identification of geological materials can be used as a fast and objective method to describe samples, drill cores, trench exposures and outcrops.</Abstract>
  <Title>Automated Classification and Correlation of Drill Cores using High-Resolution Hyperspectral Images and Supervised Pattern Classification Algorithms. Applications to Paleoseismology</Title>
  <Session>IN11A</Session>
  <Hour>0800h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Ragona, D E</Name><Email>dragona@ucsd.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Institute of Geophysics and Planetary Physics, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of California, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla, CA 92093 United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Minster, B</Name><Email>jbminster@ucsd.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Institute of Geophysics and Planetary Physics, Scripps Institution of Oceanography, University of California, 9500 Gilman Drive, La Jolla, CA 92093 United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Rockwell, T</Name><Email>trockwell@geology.sdsu.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Geology Department, San Diego State University, 5500 Campanille Drive, San Diego, CA 92182 United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Jasso, H</Name><Email>hjasso@cs.ucsd.edu</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
