<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2006 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN42A-04</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0430  Computational methods and data processing</Keyword>
    <Keyword>1622  Earth system modeling</Keyword>
    <Keyword>1640  Remote sensing</Keyword>
    <Keyword>9320  Asia</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>The potential of Spatial Data Infrastructures (SDI) to share geoinformation and services over the Internet has been widely recognized and various initiatives (e.g. INSPIRE, GMES, GEOSS) are actively engaged to implement such systems on local, national or global level. Standards published by the Open Geospatial Consortium (OGC), the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) or the World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) provide the basis for distributed yet interoperable SDI&apos;s. Following the available guidelines and standards the Siberian Earth System Science Cluster (SIB-ESS-C) is being developed as a spatial data infrastructure for remote sensing product generation, data dissemination and scientific data analysis. This paper describes the concept of the Siberian Earth System Science Cluster. SIB-ESS-C emerged from the EU funded SIBERIA-II project (EVG2-2001-00008, 2002-2005) which was a joint Russian-European remote sensing project focusing on a 300 Million ha area in the central Siberian region. This area represents a significant part of the Earth&apos;s boreal biome which plays a critical role in global climate change in Northern Eurasia. The overall objective of the SIBERIA-II project was to demonstrate the viability of full carbon accounting including greenhouse gases (GHG) on a regional basis using state-of-the-art environmental methods and advanced remote sensing technologies. The tools and systems which have been employed include a selected yet spectrally and temporally diverse set of 15 Earth observation instruments on 8 satellites, detailed GIS databases and Dynamic Global Vegetation Models to account for fluxes between land and atmosphere. The data sets and value-added products created within the SIBERIA-II project will form the basic set of products for SIB-ESS-C. These products include regional maps of land cover, fire induced disturbances, phenology, snow depth, snow melt date, onset and duration of freeze and thaw, LAI and others. Since these products have been derived from various sensors using specific methods they differ greatly in terms of data type (e.g. binary raster, vector), spatial resolution, acquisition frequency or temporal aggregation. One of the objectives of SIB-ESS-C is to make these products accessible through standard web services. The overall design philosophy of SIB-ESS-C follows two major principles: i) adhere to international de-facto standards to ensure interoperability and ii) implement free and open source software components whenever possible. In keeping with it, the architecture of SIB-ESS-C shall comprise OGC compliant components, e.g. a Catalog Service for Web (CSW) for data discovery, a Web Coverage Service (WCS) for data access, a Web Map Service (WMS) for data viewing and in the future a Web Processing Service (WPS) for on-demand product creation. The core of SIB-ESS-C will be a small PC cluster ensuring continuous product generation to build up time series. Further, SIB-ESS-C shall contain comprehensive online analysis tools allowing users to visually exploit the information content of the data sets provided. The Siberian Earth System Science Cluster is being supported by the Friedrich-Schiller University Jena (Germany) for the period commencing January 2006 until December 2010.</Abstract>
  <Title>SIB-ESS-C - A Spatial Data Infrastructure to Facilitate Earth System Science in Siberia</Title>
  <Session>IN42A</Session>
  <Hour>11:05h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Schmullius, C C</Name><Email>c.schmullius@uni-jena.de</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Friedrich-Schiller University, Institute of Geography, Department of Earth Observation, Loebdergraben 32, Jena, 07737 Germany</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Gerlach, R</Name><Email>roman.gerlach@uni-jena.de</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Friedrich-Schiller University, Institute of Geography, Department of Earth Observation, Loebdergraben 32, Jena, 07737 Germany</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Hese, S</Name><Email>soeren.hese@uni-jena.de</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
