<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2007 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN31C-02</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0430  Computational methods and data processing</Keyword>
    <Keyword>0476  Plant ecology</Keyword>
    <Keyword>0480  Remote sensing</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>A NASA RPC (Rapid Prototyping Capability) experiment was conducted to assess the potential of VIIRS (Visible/Infrared Imager/Radiometer Suite) data for monitoring non-native gypsy moth (Lymantria dispar) defoliation of forests. This experiment compares defoliation detection products computed from simulated VIIRS and from MODIS (Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer) time series products as potential inputs to a forest threat EWS (Early Warning System) being developed for the USFS (USDA Forest Service). Gypsy moth causes extensive defoliation of broadleaved forests in the United States and is specifically identified in the Healthy Forest Restoration Act (HFRA) of 2003. The HFRA mandates development of a national forest threat EWS. This system is being built by the USFS, and NASA is aiding integration of needed satellite data products into this system, including MODIS products. This RPC experiment enabled the MODIS follow-on, VIIRS, to be evaluated as a data source for EWS forest monitoring products. The experiment included 1) assessment of MODIS-simulated VIIRS NDVI products, and 2) evaluation of  gypsy moth defoliation mapping products from MODIS-simulated VIIRS and from MODIS NDVI time series data. This experiment employed MODIS data collected over the approx. 15 million acre mid-Appalachian Highlands during the annual peak defoliation time frame (June 10 through July 27) during 2000-2006. NASA Stennis Application Research Toolbox software was used to produce MODIS-simulated VIIRS data and NASA Stennis Time Series Product Tool software was employed to process MODIS and MODIS-simulated VIIRS time series data scaled to planetary reflectance. MODIS-simulated VIIRS data was assessed through comparison to Hyperion-simulated VIIRS data using data collected during gypsy moth defoliation. Hyperion- simulated MODIS data showed a high correlation with actual MODIS data. MODIS-simulated VIIRS data for the same date showed moderately high correlation with Hyperion-simulated VIIRS data, even though the datasets were collected about a half an hour apart during changing weather conditions. MODIS products (MOD02, MOD09, and MOD13) and MOD02-simulated VIIRS time series data were used to generate defoliation mapping products based on image classification and image differencing change detection techniques. Accuracy of final defoliation mapping products was assessed by image interpretation of over 170 randomly sampled locations found on Landsat and ASTER data in conjunction with defoliation map data from the USFS. The MOD02-simulated VIIRS 400-m NDVI classification produced a similar overall accuracy to the MOD02 250-m NDVI classification. MOD02 and MOD02-simulated VIIRS data both showed promise as data sources for regional monitoring of forest disturbance due to insect defoliation.</Abstract>
  <Title>Potential of VIIRS Data for Regional Monitoring of Gypsy Moth Defoliation: Implications for Forest Threat Early Warning System</Title>
  <Session>IN31C</Session>
  <Hour>08:30h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Spruce, J P</Name><Email>Joseph.P.Spruce@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Science Systems and Applications, Inc., Bldg. 1105, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Ryan, R E</Name><Email>Robert.E.Ryan@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Science Systems and Applications, Inc., Bldg. 1105, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Smoot, J C</Name><Email>James.C.Smoot@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Science Systems and Applications, Inc., Bldg. 1105, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Prados, D L</Name><Affiliations><Affiliation>Computer Sciences Corporation, Bldg. 1105, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>McKellip, R D</Name><Affiliations><Affiliation>National Aeronautics and Space Administration, Code PA11, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Sader, S A</Name><Affiliations><Affiliation>School of Forest Resources, University of Maine, 260 Nutting Hall, Orono, ME 04469, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Gasser, G</Name><Affiliations><Affiliation>Lockheed Martin Mission Services - Civil Programs, Bldg. 5100, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>May, G</Name><Affiliations><Affiliation>Institute for Technology Development, Bldg. 1103, Stennis Space Center, MS 39529, United  States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Hargrove, W</Name></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
