<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2008 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN31D-10</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0525  Data management</Keyword>
    <Keyword>9315  Arctic region</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>The National Science Foundation (NSF) and the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, under the  auspices of the U.S. Inter-Agency Arctic Research Policy Committee, are leading the development of the Arctic Observing Network (AON) as part of the implementation of the Study of Environmental Arctic Change (SEARCH) and as a legacy of International Polar Year (IPY). As the Observing Change component of SEARCH, AON complements the Understanding Change and Responding to Change components. AON addresses the need to enhance observing capabilities in a data-sparse region where environmental system changes are among the most rapid on Earth. AON data will contribute to research into understanding the causes and consequences of Arctic environmental system change and its global connections, and to improving predictive skill. AON is also a contribution to the development of a multi-nation, pan-Arctic observing network that is being discussed at the IPY &apos;Sustaining Arctic Observing Networks&apos; (SAON) workshops. Enhancing Arctic observing capabilities faces many challenges, including coordination and integration of disparate observing elements and data systems that operate according to diverse policies and practices. There is wide agreement that data systems that provide archiving and discovery services are essential and integral to AON. In recognition of this, NSF is supporting the development of CADIS (Cooperative Arctic Data and Information Service) as an AON portal for data discovery, a repository for data storage, and a platform for data analysis. NSF is also supporting ELOKA (Exchange for Local Observations and Knowledge in the Arctic), a pilot project for a data management and networking service for community- based observing that keeps control of data in the hands of data providers while still allowing for broad searches and sharing of information. CADIS and ELOKA represent the application of cyberinfrastructure to meet AON data system needs that might also contribute to the virtual, physical and social coordination and integration that will be required to create a functioning network that will realise Arctic and global value-added services and societal benefits. Enhanced Arctic observing and data systems also need a data policy. The AON data policy is clear and the same as the SEARCH data policy: data must be fully, freely and openly available as quickly as possible after collection and quality control. That is, with few exceptions, AON data are  community data and not subject to embargo. Successful implementation of this policy will require something of a cultural shift among many scientists and northern residents. Sustained, inter-operable data systems that make it easy to deposit and discover data have a role to play a role in achieving that cultural shift.</Abstract>
  <Title>Arctic Observing Network (AON): Enhancing Observing, Data Archiving and Data Discovery Capabilities as Arctic Environmental System Change Continues</Title>
  <Session>IN31D</Session>
  <Hour>09:45h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Jeffries, M O</Name><Email>mjeffrie@nsf.gov</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
