<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2008 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN11B-1026</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0496  Water quality</Keyword>
    <Keyword>0525  Data management</Keyword>
    <Keyword>0530  Data presentation and visualization</Keyword>
    <Keyword>1880  Water management</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>IINTRODUCTION The Health-e-Waterways Project is a three way collaboration between the University of Queensland, Microsoft Research and the Healthy Waterways Partnership (SEQ-HWP)(over 60 local government, state agency, universities, community and environmental organizations). The project is developing a highly innovative framework and set of services to enable streamlined access to an integrated collection of real- time, near-real-time and static datasets acquired through ecosystem monitoring programs in South East Queensland. Using a novel combination of semantic web technologies, scientific data servers, web services, GIS visualization interfaces and scientific workflows, we are enabling the sharing and integration of high quality data and models, through a combined integrated water information management system and Web portal. DYNAMIC GENERATION OF ECOSYSTEM HEALTH REPORT CARDS SEQ-HWP is responsible for the Ecosystem Health Monitoring Program (EHMP)  in South East Queensland. This currently involves sampling 30 freshwater indicators at 100 sites twice a year and 250 estuarine/marine sites every month. The EHMP data sets are statistically aggregated and standardized to produce ecosystem health grades that are published annually in hard copy EHMP Report Cards.  Politicians and planners  use the report cards to make decisions with respect to land use, water quality, allocations and investments in water recycling plants etc. To date, these report cards have been largely produced manually, by calculating standardized scores (0-1) across 5 indicators and 16 indices (physical, chemical, nutrients, ecosystem processes, acquatic macroinvertebrates and fish) and grades from A-F for each catchment and season (spring and autumn). Currently this process takes about 5 months. For the past 6 months, we have been working with the SEQ-HWP staff, developing software services that will enable the report cards to be generated dynamically via a Web-based Map interface to an underlying database that contains the EHMP water quality and quantity monitoring data. The GUI enables users to specify and query: - Spatial regions of interest through a GoogleEarth or the Microsoft VirtualEarth interface. - Concepts or indicators of interest through the EHMPOntology. - Seasons or years of interest through a timeline. A Report Card Grade is generated for the specified catchment and period. Users can retrieve raw data by clicking on a grade  this displays the corresponding EcoH plot, dynamically generated from the 5 indicators in  the underlying SQL Server database. Clicking on an EcoH plot, displays the actual raw data (16 indices) used to generate the indicators and plots. CONCLUSIONS Numerous state, national and international agencies are advocating the need for standardized frameworks and procedures for environmental accounting. The Health-e-Waterways project provides an ideal model for delivering a standardized approach to the aggregation of ecosystem health monitoring data and the generation of dynamic, interactive Report Cards (that incorporate links back to the raw data sets). The system we have described here will not only save agencies significant time and money, but it can be used to guide regional, state and national environmental policy development, based on accurate and timely evidential  data.</Abstract>
  <Title>Linking Management Actions to Interactive Ecosystem Report Cards via an Ontology</Title>
  <Session>IN11B</Session>
  <Hour>0800h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Alabri, A</Name><Email>alabri@itee.uq.edu.au</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>University of Queensland, St Lucia, Queensland, Australia, Brisbane, Qld 4072, Australia</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Newman, A</Name><Email>anewman@itee.uq.edu.au</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>University of Queensland, St Lucia, Queensland, Australia, Brisbane, Qld 4072, Australia</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Abal, E</Name><Email>e.abal@uq.edu.au</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Healthy Waterways Partnership, George Street, Brisbane, Qld 4001, Australia</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>van Ingen, C</Name><Email>vaningen@microsoft.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Microsoft Research, 835 Market St, San Francisco, CA 94103, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Hunter, J</Name><Email>j.hunter@uq.edu.au</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
