<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2009 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics</Section>
  <Id>IN34B-08</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Cyberinfrastructure</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Data assimilation, integration and fusion</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Emerging informatics technologies</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Metadata: Quality</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>The single greatest problem with the federation of scientific data is the assessment of the quality and validity of the aggregated data in the context of particular research problems, that is, its fitness for use. There are three critical data quality issues in networks of distributed natural science collections data, as in all scientific data: identifying and correcting errors, maintaining currency, and assessing fitness for use. To this end, we have designed and implemented a prototype network in the domain of natural science collections. This prototype is built over the open source Map-Reduce platform Hadoop with a network client in the open source collections management system Specify 6. We call this network &amp;#8220;Filtered Push&amp;#8221; as, at its core, annotations are pushed from the network edges to relevant authoritative repositories, where humans and software filter the annotations before accepting them as changes to the authoritative data. The Filtered Push software is a domain-neutral framework for originating, distributing, and analyzing record-level annotations. Network participants can subscribe to notifications arising from ontology-based analyses of new annotations or of purpose-built queries against the network&apos;s global history of annotations. Quality and fitness for use of distributed natural science collections data can be addressed with Filtered Push software by implementing a network that allows data providers and consumers to define potential errors in data, develop metrics for those errors, specify workflows to analyze distributed data to detect potential errors, and to close the quality management cycle by providing a network architecture to pushing assertions about data quality such as corrections back to the curators of the participating data sets. Quality issues in distributed scientific data have several things in common: (1) Statements about data quality should be regarded as hypotheses about inconsistencies between perhaps several records, data sets, or practices of science. (2) Data quality problems often cannot be detected only from internal statistical correlations or logical analysis, but may need the application of defined workflows that signal illogical output. (3) Changes in scientific theory or practice over time can result in changes of what QC tests should be applied to legacy data. (4) The frequency of some classes of error in a data set may be identifiable without the ability to assert that a particular record is in error. To address these issues requires, as does science itself, framing QC hypotheses against data that may be anywhere and may arise at any time in the future. In short, QC for science data is a never ending process. It must provide for notice to an agent (human or software) that a given dataset supports a hypothesis of inconsistency with a current scientific resource or model, or with potential generalizations of the concepts in a metadata ontology. Like quality control in general, quality control of distributed data is a repeated cyclical process. In implementing a Filtered Push network for quality control, we have a model in which the cost of QC forever is not substantially greater than QC once.</Abstract>
  <Title>Filtered Push: Annotating Distributed Data for Quality Control and Fitness for Use Analysis</Title>
  <Session>IN34B</Session>
  <Hour>1745h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Morris, P J</Name><Email>mole@morris.net</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>HUH &amp;amp; MCZ, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Kelly, M A</Name><Email>mkelly@oeb.harvard.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>HUH, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Lowery, D B</Name><Email>lowerydb@gmail.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>CS, UMass Boston, Boston, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Macklin, J A</Name><Email>jmacklin@oeb.harvard.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>HUH, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Morris, R A</Name><Email>morris.bob@gmail.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>CS, UMass Boston, Boston, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Tremonte, D</Name><Email>dtremont@oeb.harvard.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>HUH, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, United States</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Wang, Z</Name><Email>wangzm@cs.umb.edu</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
