<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2010 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics</Section>
  <Id>IN31A-1252</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Data assimilation, integration and fusion</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>NASA&amp;#8217;s MODIS Rapid Response Project (http://rapidfire.sci.gsfc.nasa.gov/) has been providing MODIS fire detections and imagery in near real-time since 2001. The Rapid Response system is part of the Land and Atmospheres Near-real time Capability for EOS (LANCE-MODIS) system. Current capabilities include providing MODIS imagery in true color and false color band combinations, a vegetation index, and temperature - in both uncorrected swath format and geographically corrected subset regions. The geographically-corrected subsets images cover the world&apos;s land areas and adjoining waters, as well as the entire Arctic and Antarctic. These data are available within a few hours of data acquisition. The images are accessed by large number of user communities to obtain a rapid, 250 meter-resolution overview of ground conditions for fire management, crop and famine monitoring and forecasting, disaster response (fires, oil spills, floods, storms), dust and aerosol monitoring, aviation (tracking volcanic ash), monitoring sea ice conditions, environmental monitoring, and more. In addition, the scientific community uses imagery to locate phenomena of interest prior to ordering and processing data and to support the day-to-day planning of field campaigns. The MODIS Rapid Response project has also been providing a near real-time data feed on fire locations and MODIS imagery subsets to the Fire Information for Resource Management System (FIRMS) project (http://maps.geog.umd.edu/firms). FIRMS provides timely availability of fire location information, which is essential in preventing and fighting large forest/wild fires. Products are available through a WebGIS for visualizing MODIS hotspots and MCD45 Burned Area images, an email alerting tool to deliver fire data on daily/weekly/near real-time basis, active data downloads in formats such as shape, KML, CSV, WMS, etc., along with MODIS imagery subsets. FIRMS&amp;#8217; user base covers more than 100 countries and territories. A recent user survey showed that a majority of people use FIRMS for the purposes of conservation, fire-fighting, natural hazard monitoring, land cover change monitoring, and climate change. FIRMS has also developed a cellphone-based text (SMS) alerting of MODIS and MSG-detected fires in near real-time in South Africa, in partnership with the South African power company ESKOM and Council of Scientific and Industrial Research, South Africa. FIRMS was transitioned to the United Nations Food and Agricultural Organization (UN-FAO) in Rome, Italy in Spring 2010 and is scheduled to become a part of the LANCE-MODIS data system (http://lance.nasa.gov/) in Spring 2011.</Abstract>
  <Title>Applications of Near Real-Time Image and Fire Products from MODIS</Title>
  <Session>IN31A</Session>
  <Hour>0800h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Schmaltz, J E</Name><Email>Jeff.Schmaltz@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Sigma Space Corporation, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Ilavajhala, S</Name><Email>shriram@hermes.geog.umd.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Sigma Space Corporation, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Teague, M</Name><Email>Michael.Teague@sigmaspace.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Sigma Space Corporation, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Ye, G</Name><Email>Gang.Ye@sigmaspace.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Sigma Space Corporation, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Masuoka, E</Name><Email>Edward.J.Masuoka@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Code 614.5, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Davies, D</Name><Email>ddavies@hermes.geog.umd.edu</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>University of Maryland, College Park, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Murphy, K J</Name><Email>Kevin.j.Murphy@nasa.gov</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Code 423, Goddard Space Flight Center, Greenbelt, MD, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Michael, K</Name><Email>karen.a.michael@nasa.gov</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
