<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2010 Meeting of the Americas</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics</Section>
  <Id>IN21A-04</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Data management, preservation, rescue</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>Several space monitoring instruments are simultaneously acquiring different types of data for a long time. Their outputs usually have particular file formats, and information organization. This work presents a case study for database development using a space monitoring instrument. The Multidirectional Muon Detector Database (MMD-DB) was implemented based on a Multidirectional Muon Detector (MMD), assembled at National Institute for Space Research (INPE), Southern Spacial Observatory (SSO), located in S&amp;#227;o Martinho da Serra, Brazil. The MMD is capable of performing directional measurements of secondary cosmic rays incidence. Those measurements are important for analysis and prediction of solar events, and generate data in text files every hour. The first step of MMD-DB construction was to carefully study the instrument functioning, output files and data structure. All information that should be stored on database was identified, including data not present on the output files, such as the instrument technical description, exact location, calibrations, etc. After that, the appropriated deployment tools could be chosen. It is important to stress that, despite there are many different and innovative technologies, we focused only on those tools that satisfied some criteria. They should present extensive documentation, be largely used and tested (kind of &amp;#8220;standard&amp;#8221; in the area), and, preferably, be used (and modified) free of charge. As a result, we decided to use a relational database, logically implemented using PosgreSQL 8.1. Java programming language associated with Hibernate framework was used to load data from the text files into database. The programming environment was NetBeans IDE 6.5. The final database model implemented a total of 8 tables. All relations between tables were the type of 1:N. A total of 2325 files were loaded into database, during a process that took more than 40 hours to be completed, and provided approximately 22 millions of registers on the tables. In the future, it is expected the development of a Web-based interface to allow researchers to access data from the MMD-DB, using different types of queries. Another target of this work is to add information from the other MMDs that constitute the Global Muon Detector Network (GMDN).</Abstract>
  <Title>Database development for space monitoring instruments: case study for Multidirectional Muon Detector Database (MMD-DB)</Title>
  <Session>IN21A</Session>
  <Hour>0845h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Petry, A</Name><Email>adriano.petry@crs.inpe.br</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Southern Regional Space Research Center, National Institute for Space Research, Santa Maria, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Kato, C</Name><Email>ckato@shinshu-u.ac.jp</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Shinshu University, Shinshu, Japan</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Bueno, J</Name><Email>julianapb@gmail.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Associated Laboratory of Computing and Applied Mathematics, National Institute for Space Research, S&amp;#227;o Jos&amp;#233; dos Campos, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>da Silva, M R</Name><Email>marlos@dge.inpe.br</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Spatial Geophysics Division, National Institute for Space Research, S&amp;#227;o Jos&amp;#233; dos Campos, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Ramos, L</Name><Email>lucasfisico@gmail.com</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Spatial Geophysics Division, National Institute for Space Research, S&amp;#227;o Jos&amp;#233; dos Campos, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Kemmerich, N</Name><Email>nikolas@lacesm.ufsm.br</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Southern Regional Space Research Center, National Institute for Space Research, Santa Maria, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Dal Lago, A</Name><Email>dallago@dge.inpe.br</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Spatial Geophysics Division, National Institute for Space Research, S&amp;#227;o Jos&amp;#233; dos Campos, Brazil</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Schuch, N J</Name><Email>njschuch@lacesm.ufsm.br</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
