<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>2010 Fall Meeting</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics</Section>
  <Id>IN23C-07</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Knowledge representation and knowledge bases</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Portals and user interfaces</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Real-time and responsive information delivery</Keyword>
    <Keyword>INFORMATICS / Social networks</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>In support of complex water-resource sustainability projects in the Great Basin region of the United States, Earth Knowledge, Inc. has developed several web-based data management and analysis platforms that have been used by its scientists, clients, and public to facilitate information exchanges, collaborations, and decision making. These platforms support accurate water-resource decision-making by combining second-generation internet (Web 2.0) technologies with traditional 2D GIS and web-based 2D and 3D mapping systems such as Google Maps, and Google Earth. Most data management and analysis systems use traditional software systems to address the data needs and usage behavior of the scientific community. In contrast, these platforms employ more accessible open-source and &amp;#8220;off-the-shelf&amp;#8221; consumer-oriented, hosted web-services. They exploit familiar software tools using industry standard protocols, formats, and APIs to discover, process, fuse, and visualize earth, engineering, and social science datasets. Thus, they respond to the information needs and web-interface expectations of both subject-matter experts and the public. Because the platforms continue to gather and store all the contributions of their broad-spectrum of users, each new assessment leverages the data, information, and expertise derived from previous investigations. In the last year, Earth Knowledge completed a conceptual system design and feasibility study for a platform, which has a Knowledge Portal providing access to users wishing to retrieve information or knowledge developed by the science enterprise and a Collaboration Environment Module, a framework that links the user-access functions to a Technical Core supporting technical and scientific analyses including Data Management, Analysis and Modeling, and Decision Management, and to essential system administrative functions within an Administrative Module. The over-riding technical challenge is the design and development of a single technical platform that is accessed through a flexible series of knowledge portal and collaboration environment styles reflecting the information needs and user expectations of a diverse community of users. Recent investigations have defined the information needs and expectations of the major end-users and also have reviewed and assessed a wide variety of modern web-based technologies. Combining these efforts produced design specifications and recommendations for the selection and integration of web- and client-based tools. When fully developed, the resulting platform will: -Support new, advanced information systems and decision environments that take full advantage of multiple data sources and platforms; -Provide a distribution network tailored to the timely delivery of products to a broad range of users that are needed to support applications in disaster management, resource management, energy, and urban sustainability; -Establish new integrated multiple-user requirements and knowledge databases that support researchers and promote infusion of successful technologies into existing processes; and -Develop new decision support strategies and presentation methodologies for applied earth science applications to reduce risk, cost, and time.</Abstract>
  <Title>A Web-Based Earth-Systems Knowledge Portal and Collaboration Platform</Title>
  <Session>IN23C</Session>
  <Hour>1500h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>D&apos;Agnese, F A</Name><Email>frank@earthknowledge.net</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>Earth Knowledge, Inc., Tucson, AZ, USA</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Turner, A K</Name><Email>kturner@mines.edu</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
