<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<AGUAbstract xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema http://www.agu.org/focus_group/essi/schema/agu.xsd">
  <Meeting>Fall Meeting 2005</Meeting>
  <Section>Earth and Space Science Informatics [IN]</Section>
  <Id>IN44A-05</Id>
  <Keywords>
    <Keyword>0525  Data management</Keyword>
    <Keyword>0530  Data presentation and visualization</Keyword>
  </Keywords>
  <Abstract>The CDEX (Center for Deep Earth Exploration, JAMSTEC) is an implementing organization of a riser drilling vessel, CHIKYU (&quot;Earth&quot;).  CHIKYU has a large capability to produce a wide variety of data, core measurement data, logging data, mud logging  data, cuttings data and monitoring data in boreholes, etc.  Also CDEX conducts site survey for safety drilling and publication before and after cruises.  It is critical that these diverse data be managed using a unified, coherent method, and that they be organized and provided to users in an intuitive, clearly understandable way that reflects the aims and underlying philosophies of the IODP and JAMSTEC.  It is crucial that these data are accessible to users through an integrated  interface in which all data formats, management tools, and procedures are standardized.  Meeting these goals will assure total usability for scientists, administrators, and the public, from data creation to uploading and cataloging, to end use and publication.      CDEX is developing an integrated information management system, call &quot;SIO7&quot; (Scientific Information from 7 Oceans) for CHIKYU operation, and would like to extend to adopt various information handling systems in geosciences.  The SIO7 composed of 2 major systems, J-CORES (JAMSTEC Core Systematics) and DEXIS (Deep Earth Exploration Information System) (see http://sio7.jamstec.go.jp/ for the details).  J-CORES is a database system designated to manage all aspects of core data. The system is modeled on the JANUS system developed by and for ODP, but implements an extended, somewhat modified data model.   The functions that support onboard and real time data input operations have also been strengthened.  A variety of data visualization and visual core description functions have been added, and data loading from those applications has been automated, making the system as a whole both powerful and easy to use.  On the other hand, DEXIS is developed based on the combination and integration of existing off-the-shelf application software that are tuned-up and optimized.  DEXIS comprised two main functions: data browsing and data interpretation.  The functions are available to use though an internet at anytime and from anywhere users want.  Most standard data format are accepted for site survey data and logging data and GIS functions  are involved.      We will coordinate more data items in SIO7 with other JAMSTEC data that archived and provided data services by different  systems.  Also we will try to provide data tools and/or applications to contribute international colleagues who are working in geoscience fields.  J-CORES is an open source application, and we encourage users to educate how to use the tools.</Abstract>
  <Title>An Information Management System for CHIKYU Operation and its Future</Title>
  <Session>IN44A</Session>
  <Hour>17:00h</Hour>
  <Authors>
    <Author><Name>Kuramoto, S</Name><Email>s.kuramoto@jamstec.go.jp</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>CDEX/JAMSTEC, 3173-25 Showa-machi, Kanazawa-ku, Yokohama, 236-0001  Japan</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Matsuda, S</Name><Email>matsudas@jamstec.go.jp</Email><Affiliations><Affiliation>CDEX/JAMSTEC, 3173-25 Showa-machi, Kanazawa-ku, Yokohama, 236-0001  Japan</Affiliation></Affiliations></Author>
    <Author><Name>Ito, H</Name><Email>hisaoito@jamstec.go.jp</Email></Author>
  </Authors>
</AGUAbstract>
